[
    {
        "question": "Se abbod grete þone (<em>cyning</em>) #### — The abbot greets the king",
        "correctAnswer": "cyning",
        "explanation":"Here 'cyning' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen sloh þone (<em>biscop</em>) #### in tæm tune — The thane slew the bishop in the town",
        "correctAnswer": "biscop",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða biscopas geaf þone (<em>stan</em>) #### to þaem þegne — The bishops gave the stone to the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "stan",
        "explanation":"Here 'stan' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ond seo cwen grete þa (<em>biscop</em>) #### — The king and the queen greet the bishops",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopas",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning sloh þa (<em>þegen</em>) #### — The king slew the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnas|þegenas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen geaf þa (<em>gar</em>) #### to þaem cyninge — The thane gives the spears to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "garas",
        "explanation":"Here 'gar' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm biscop geaf se cyning þa (<em>beag</em>) #### — The king gave rings to the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "beagas",
        "explanation":"Here 'beag' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm (<em>cyning</em>) #### geaf se biscop beag — To the king, the bishop gave a ring",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninge",
        "explanation":"Here 'cyning' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending.",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "cyning",
                "explanation": "Cyning is the nominative or accusative singular form of the word. Here 'cyning' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending."
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen ferþ to þæm (<em>biscop</em>) #### mid wordum fram þæm cyning — The thane goes to the bishop with words from the king",
        "correctAnswer": "biscope",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "biscop",
                "explanation": "Biscop is the nominative or accusative singular form of the word. Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending."
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop ferde fram þæm (<em>þegen</em>) #### to þæm cyning — The bishop went from the thane to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "þegne|þegene",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þis daeg, Æðelred cyning ferde to þæm (<em>tun</em>) #### mid broðor— On this day, King Ethelred went to the town with his brother",
        "correctAnswer": "tune",
        "explanation":"Here 'tun' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ferþ to þæm (<em>beorg</em>) #### — The king goes to the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "beorgum",
        "explanation":"Here 'beorg' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it is in the plural dative and thus takes the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wærferhþ biscop ferde to þæm (<em>biscop</em>) #### in Lundene ond Wiltunscire — Bishop Warfehth went to the bishops of London and Wiltshire",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopum",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the plural dative and thus takes the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se geaf þa garas to þæm (<em>þegen</em>) #### — He gave the spears to the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnum|þegenum",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the plural dative and thus takes the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se abbot com fram þæm (<em>beorg</em>) #### - The abbot came from the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "beorgum",
        "explanation":"Here 'beorg' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'com', so it is in the plural dative and thus takes the 'um' ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop ferþ to þæm halige (<em>stede</em>) #### - The bishop goes to the holy place",
        "correctAnswer": "stede",
        "explanation":"Here 'stede' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",        
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
            "incorrectAnswer": "stedee",
            "explanation":"While 'stede' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ' and so is dative singular, it already ends in e, so no additional letters are added"        
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie þreowon þa (<em>gar</em>) #### at þæm wicingum - They threw the spears at the vikings",
        "correctAnswer": "garas",
        "explanation":"Here 'gar' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'þreowon', so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He æt þone (<em>fugol</em>) #### - He ate the bird",
        "correctAnswer": "fugol",
        "explanation":"Here 'fugol' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'æt', so it is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða biscopas comon fram þæm (<em>tun</em>) #### Londenum ond Readingum gehatan — The bishops came from the towns called London and Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "tunum",
        "explanation":"Here 'tun' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'comon', so it is in the plural dative and thus takes the 'um' ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]



